[Music]
hi everyone this is RI welcome to Tri
Anda automation
tutorial so this is our lesson
13 as part of our Advanced Training and
this is our lesson 28 as part of our
overall tricentis Taska automation
training so as you all know I've already
published part one of conditional
statements and Loops where I've have
teached you about if
else if then else conditions how can we
use if then else conditions in prent
tasa while automating your test cases so
this is our part two of conditional
statements and Loops in this lesson
you'll learn how can we use do
statements while automating your test
cases please do subscribe to the channel
click on Bell icon you'll receive
notifications whenever I publish more
videos thank
you so first of all let us understand
what is do conditional statement so when
you create do statements TSA will
automatically create two objects the
first object is a loop object allow on
with the second object called condition
object so test steps within the loop
object whatever you define are run
repeatedly until the condition is long
no longer fulfilled so the result of the
repetition is th a
negative so do statements contain the
property called maximum repetitions in
order to avoid in infinite Loops so the
value column shows the maximum number of
attempts for a test steps to be run so
the default value is set as
30 and let us the see the order of our
conditions so order is like this first
you will have a do condition and then
Loop condition within the do statement
and then you will have a condition
within the do statement okay this is the
order so now let us jump onto the system
and automate one of the test case or
scenario by using do conditional
statements so let me jump onto my trient
tosa so this is my trient tosa right so
what I'm going to do I'm going to create
one new
folder and I'm going to name this as
shopping cart okay I'm going to name
this as shopping cart and let us first
create one test case within this
folder I'm going to say
empty
shopping cart empty shopping cart okay
I'm going to name this as empty shopping
cart so now let us first understand what
is the scenario that we are going to
automate okay so let us first understand
so this is my shopping cart okay in
shopping cart I have total four
different items okay if you see the
shopping cart is not empty it has an
existing items so now I want to empty
this shopping cart before I start my
test case execution whenever I login I
want to make sure that the shopping cart
is empty for that first you need to read
number of items in the shopping cart and
then you need to check the item that you
want to delete see first I'm going to
check the first item and then update
shopping
cart and then again I'm going to select
second item update shopping cart so
basically we are removing it so remove
this and update shopping cart if you
have items here in the shopping cart
again yes and then check it and then
update shopping cart so we are going to
perform this action until the shopping
cart is empty correct so that is what I
want to automate first I want to empty
the shopping cart if the items are
present if the items are not present
then you need to come out okay so let us
first let's make sure we add couple of
items okay let me add this blue jeans
and let me also add this as well into
the cart
and then I'm going to add my this one
belt and also I'm going to add a shoe
okay so I'm just making sure the
shopping cart has some items okay now I
have items so let's go back to our
Trenta so to empty the shopping cart
what is our first step our first step is
you need to go to your shopping cart you
need to click on shopping cart okay
let's go here
for that I want to insert a step called
top menu so I already covered all these
we already captured all the modules that
are required in our previous sessions
right so I'm just capturing I'm calling
top menu module right and here I want to
click on shopping cut right so let us
just put it as X okay done once I click
on shopping cart and then I'll perform
emptying the shopping cart operation by
using do statement later what I have to
do I have to click on log out okay now
emptying shopping cart by using do do
statement I'll insert later okay after
that you going to do log out let's do
log out okay for that again you need to
call Top menu correct top menu and then
here this time you need to click on log
out and then you need to close the
browser right so for that again you can
use the standard module close browser
standard module right and then I'm going
to name this as demo star okay done so
now so let us go back to our shopping
cart so once
I come to shopping cart now I need to
read the web table this product table
right and then check the item if this
product I mean if the shopping cart has
a product table then you need to remove
all these items okay first let us insert
the do statement okay how can you insert
do statement right click on your test
case and if you see here creative
statement I already explained you in my
previous session so this is our part two
where I'm going to start with create do
statement and then next part three you
will have where I'm going to explain
about while statements okay so as part
of part two let's select create do
statement okay and I want to bring this
here as soon as I come to shopping cart
now I come to shopping
cart let's expand this and let us go to
do statement okay once I come to
shopping cart I need to
remove the existing items correct what I
want to do first you are going to define
the loop what do you want to do and how
many number of times correct so Loop
under Loop now I want to insert shopping
cart I'm going to take my shopping cart
module under Loop and
here expand this product card table what
is this one this is your table this is
your web table right this entire web
table so go to your web table expand
row right what I'm going to do I have to
Define first I want to make this as my
first row I want to go for the first row
anytime dollar one that means I am
instructing to go to the table and check
for the first row okay dollar one and
once you check the first row I want to
select the column what is the column
this is remove column this is product
column price quantity so I want to
select product column sorry remove
column okay once I select the remove
column I don't want to verify this I
want to select this okay select the
column once I select the column you can
see there is a checkbox in this column
correct this is my remove checkbox right
so this checkbox I want to check this
checkbox so that's why I'm going to
select it as true I want to check the
checkbox and then once I check the
checkbox I want to click
on update shopping cart this one update
shopping cart so that that item will be
removed check the box and then update
shopping cart so here this is my update
shopping cart
button click on this update shopping
cart button so as soon is as soon as it
lands on to shopping cart first it
deletes first item and clicks on update
shopping cart and
now but this deletion should happen how
many times until the
condition it means the condition called
the shopping cart table does not exist
this table should be empty right so now
let us Define condition again for the
condition see I
place the cursor right click here on the
condition click on ADD test step here
again I want to add the test step called
shopping cart okay and this time what is
the condition I want to keep I want to
remove the shop um the items
until my shopping cart is visible my
shoping card table is visible so now I'm
going to make this is my shopping cart
table I'll say
exist is true equal
to
True verify I want to
verify if what is the
condition do whatever I specified here
remove the items from the shopping
cart
if this shopping cart table
exist if this shopping cart table
becomes empty this table will not be
existing so then what it will do it
comes out of the loop so basically the
last condition will be false that's why
it's not going to perform this Loop
right so done so if you say let's go
back here
again so we have completed defining
everything first we are logging into
shopping cart
and then I'm directly removing my first
item from the table because it's a do
statement do statement
is the action will be performed at least
once first it performs the action and
then it checks the condition and then
again goes back if the condition meets
it goes back to do the uh perform the
same action one more time and again
check the
condition if the condition meets if that
exist the product I mean shopping cart
products table exist again comes back
here removes the item again check the
condition if the condition does not meet
then it comes out of the loop okay so
that is done condition is done and then
once comes out the comes out of the loop
then it's going to log out and then then
close the browser okay so we have
completed our automation so now let us
run this and see how it works okay let's
go back here I want to uncheck this I
want to be in shopping cart sorry I want
let's say I want to on demo web shop
okay so now let's run this first it
should go to shopping cart okay right
click and
run see what happens first it should
click on shopping cart and then it
should remove first
item it should remove first
item I'm just just clicked so now it
should remove blue jeans see updated now
it's going to check if the table exist
and then it's removing table exist and
then it found removed now table does not
exist so it logs out and it closes the
browser see done done let's see our test
results okay let us understand the test
results
now so let us understand the test
results if you see here do statement let
us go to do statement if you see first
what it did it directly removed the
shopping cart I mean item once it
removes the shopping item it is checking
if the condition if the shopping cart
product table exist or not
so let us see here let us expand this
first it found yes this table
exist so in the same way second
condition and last one when it removed
our fourth shopping cart item right it
removed but it check the condition in
this case it should fail so here is the
shopping cart product table exist
expected is true but actually is false
that means it does not exist so it came
out of of do statement and immediately
logged out and then it closed the
browser that's it so hope you all
understand the concept
of do
statements how can we use the do
statements in tric centage tasa while
automating your test cases please do
subscribe to the channel click on Bell
icon you'll receive notifications
whenever I publish more videos thank
you